<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The FreeBSD Graphics Team</title>
    <link>http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/</link>
    <description>Recent content on The FreeBSD Graphics Team</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2014 20:10:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating xorg-dev to Git</title>
      <link>http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/post/migrating-to-git/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2014 20:10:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/post/migrating-to-git/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are experimenting with Git to replace the &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.freebsd.org/Graphics#Development_repository&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;xorg-dev” Subversion
repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, this repository is used to work on the graphics stack ports
before they go to the official Ports tree. For instance, this is where
we worked on the update to Mesa 10.3.0. Now, that Mesa 10.3.0 is
committed, xorg-dev contains Mesa 10.3.1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;xorg-dev is a Subversion repository containing only the ports and
infrastructure Makefiles which differ from the official Ports tree. The
current workflow simply consists of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;prepare a new port or update in xorg-dev&amp;rsquo;s trunk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;when ready, copy the files in a Ports tree working copy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;remove the obsolete files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;commit the change in the Ports tree&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;optionally, remove the committed work from xorg-dev&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A nice advantage is that xorg-dev remains lighweight. This makes svn
commands fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But problems arise when there are changes committed directly to the
Ports tree. We must be careful to bring those changes to xorg-dev but
from time to time, we fail to do so and they are lost. Furthermore, it&amp;rsquo;s
very hard to track history between xorg-dev and the official Ports tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s why we want to change this workflow and switch to a complete Git
clone of the Ports tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s already a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd-ports&#34;&gt;Git mirror of the Ports tree&lt;/a&gt;
available on GitHub. We are going to use this as our upstream repository
and create another repository, called &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/freebsd/freebsd-ports-graphics&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;freebsd-ports-graphics&lt;/code&gt; on
GitHub&lt;/a&gt;:
this is going to be the new xorg-dev.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will allow us to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;have a full Ports tree, so it&amp;rsquo;s easier to test: no need to merge
anything to &lt;code&gt;/usr/ports&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;handle conflicts during the developments, not when we want to commit
the final patch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keep the history in a single place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;accept GitHub pull requests from anyone (not discussed yet)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll try to use topic branches too (eg. a branch for xorg-server 1.14,
another one for Mesa 10.3.1 and so on), though this is subject to
change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.freebsd.org/Graphics/Ports_development_workflow&#34;&gt;workflow is described on the wiki&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the experiment concludes, we&amp;rsquo;ll inform you about our decision to
either keep Subversion or move to Git.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>vt(4) enabled by default</title>
      <link>http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/post/vt-enabled-by-default/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2014 20:10:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/post/vt-enabled-by-default/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;vt(4), the new console driver, is &lt;a href=&#34;http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/https://svnweb.freebsd.org/base?view=revision&amp;amp;revision=274085&#34;&gt;enabled out-of-the-box in FreeBSD
11-CURRENT&lt;/a&gt;
(the development branch of FreeBSD) as of today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who don&amp;rsquo;t know it yet, vt(4) brings important features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It &lt;strong&gt;supports Unicode&lt;/strong&gt; and double-width characters. It finally allows
to use an UTF-8 locale.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It &lt;strong&gt;integrates with the new kernel video drivers&lt;/strong&gt;. That means that
you can switch from an X session to the console and back. syscons(4)
was never taught about the KMS drivers, and this was a major
regression for users because the screen was blank when vt-switching or
terminating the X server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;vt(4) has still some issues. Furthermore, it lacks some features
compared to syscons(4). Known issues are &lt;a href=&#34;http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/https://wiki.freebsd.org/Newcons#Known_Issues&#34;&gt;listed in the
wiki&lt;/a&gt; and/or
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/buglist.cgi?keywords=vt&amp;amp;list_id=28354&amp;amp;resolution=---&#34;&gt;recorded in Bugzilla using the &amp;ldquo;vt” keyword&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Refer to the associated &lt;code&gt;UPDATING&lt;/code&gt; entry to get information about updated
console settings in &lt;code&gt;/etc/rc.conf&lt;/code&gt; or how to select syscons(4).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why kernel video drivers?</title>
      <link>http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/post/why-kernel-video-drivers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2014 20:20:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/post/why-kernel-video-drivers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many people wonder why video drivers are moved to the kernel. The
previous way of doing things was working fine and was supported by all
Unix. Now, they are afraid of switching to those kernel drivers because
they don&amp;rsquo;t understand the reason behind them and have heard about
instability and unequal levels of support between different OS versions
and GPU makers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll try to explain the reasons I know, in the hope you&amp;rsquo;ll better
understand and accept this major change in the way we use video cards
nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;X server was an operating system by itself&lt;/strong&gt;: it was able to
scan the PCI bus to find video devices and it manages the video
memory. That&amp;rsquo;s why it could work on many incompatible kernels: it
doesn&amp;rsquo;t use any of its facilities. This approach has obviously many
major issues, detailed in the following bullets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;kernel and the X server were both managing hardware&lt;/strong&gt;. This was
far from elegant and broke features such as suspend/resume.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;X server required root privileges&lt;/strong&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s why it&amp;rsquo;s
installed with the &amp;ldquo;setuid” bit set, otherwise a regular
couldn&amp;rsquo;t start an X session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;performance was terrible&lt;/strong&gt; compared to platforms (eg. Microsoft
Windows) where the video drivers are in the kernel (like any other
drivers).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The architecture of X and the tighly integrated drivers made it &lt;strong&gt;hard
to reuse the code&lt;/strong&gt; if one wants to implement an alternative, such as
Wayland. But that was true for the system console too: it needed to
drive the video card.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GPGPU wasn&amp;rsquo;t possible&lt;/strong&gt; without running an X session, because only
the X server was capable of handling the GPU.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It &lt;strong&gt;wasn&amp;rsquo;t possible to access the GPU from a virtual machine&lt;/strong&gt;, for
the same reason as above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the kernel drivers address or will address all of these issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding GPGPU using free open-source software on FreeBSD, it&amp;rsquo;s still
a work in progress. A &amp;ldquo;Hello World” OpenCL program works on my
machine, but more packaging and polishing is needed to have something
working out-of-the-box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The X server still requires root privileges today on FreeBSD because
we lack the APIs and tools to allow the server to gain access to input
devices in a secure manner (remember, the system console needs the
keyboard too).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About using the GPU from a VM, we are still far from this goal, even on
Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesa 10.3.0 committed!</title>
      <link>http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/post/mesa-10.3.0-committed/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2014 20:10:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/post/mesa-10.3.0-committed/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Today, &lt;a href=&#34;https://svnweb.freebsd.org/ports?view=revision&amp;amp;revision=371035&#34;&gt;Koop Mast committed an update to the Mesa
ports&lt;/a&gt;
to have both 9.1.7 and 10.3.0 available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-s-new:299e12da2ec80e879bf4686011266825&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s new?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mesa 10.3 brings &lt;strong&gt;major improvements in stability and performance&lt;/strong&gt;,
especially for Radeon owners, compared to Mesa 9.1. For instance, it
fixes many of the GPU lockups you may see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Mesa 10.3.0 comes a new port as well: &lt;code&gt;graphics/gbm&lt;/code&gt;. This buffer
management library is used by other components inside and outside Mesa,
such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GLAMOR, the 2D acceleration API based on OpenGL, used by at least newer Radeon cards;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weston, the reference compositor from the Wayland project;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clover, the OpenCL library in Mesa.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beside those components, the X.Org server 1.15 requires Mesa 9.2+ too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;only-for-freebsd-10-1:299e12da2ec80e879bf4686011266825&#34;&gt;Only for FreeBSD 10.1+&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still need Mesa 9.1.7 because our Intel i915 driver in FreeBSD 9.x
and FreeBSD 10.0 lacks a feature called
&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bwidawsk.net/blog/index.php/2013/01/i915-hardware-contexts-and-some-bits-about-batchbuffers/&#34;&gt;HW context&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;.
This feature allows the switch between multiple OpenGL contexts without
having to resend them to the card after each switch. Mesa 9.2 and later
versions require this. That&amp;rsquo;s why Mesa 10.3.0 can&amp;rsquo;t be used on FreeBSD
9.x or 10.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, FreeBSD 10.1 and 11-CURRENT
&lt;a href=&#34;https://svnweb.freebsd.org/base?view=revision&amp;amp;revision=271705&#34;&gt;have this feature&lt;/a&gt;.
In this case, Mesa 10.3.0 will be picked automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FreeBSD at the XDC 2014</title>
      <link>http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/post/xdc-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2014 20:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/post/xdc-2014/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;X Developer&amp;rsquo;s Conference&lt;/strong&gt; (XDC) is held every year, in
alternation between Europe and North America. This is a great
occasion for users and developers interested in the graphics stack
to meet in person and discuss. &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.x.org/wiki/Events/XDC2014/&#34;&gt;This year&amp;rsquo;s edition was in Bordeaux,
France&lt;/a&gt;, from October 8th
through 10th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;François Tigeot, from DragonFlyBSD, and I attended the conference. We
met Matthieu Herrb from OpenBSD there. The goal was to show that BSDs
are still interested in the graphics stack and that we want to work with
the community. I think that was a huge success!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a warm welcome: people were asking questions about how video
hardware was supported, how desktop environments were doing, how we are
working with the kernel drivers, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;projects-impacting-freebsd:bf650b87c593bc5b43a8309cddeddd77&#34;&gt;Projects impacting FreeBSD&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.x.org/wiki/Events/XDC2014/Program/&#34;&gt;Talks&lt;/a&gt; and discussions
were very good. I&amp;rsquo;ll sum up here what may impact FreeBSD specifically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alex Deucher (AMD)&lt;/strong&gt; talked about their &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.x.org/wiki/Events/XDC2014/XDC2014DeucherAMD/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;amdgpu&amp;rdquo;
project&lt;/a&gt;. The
purpose is to have a single open-source kernel driver, instead of the
&amp;ldquo;radeon” driver and the Catalyst driver. &amp;ldquo;radeon” will support older
generation, while &amp;ldquo;amdgpu” will support new hardware. Proprietary
components will all be in userland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Andy Ritger (NVIDIA)&lt;/strong&gt; presented two projects. First, their proposal
to allow &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.x.org/wiki/Events/XDC2014/XDC2014RitgerGLABI/&#34;&gt;multiple vendor-specific OpenGL libraries to live on the same
system&lt;/a&gt; and
even in the same process. In particular, this means no more headache
for package maintainers with libGL.so conflicts. The second project is
to change the NVIDIA proprietary kernel module to &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.x.org/wiki/Events/XDC2014/XDC2014RitgerEGLNonMesa/&#34;&gt;register as a KMS
driver&lt;/a&gt;.
This will allow them to be compatible with Wayland in the
process. Andy told me they had no special requirement on
the DRM device-independent code at that time. But our
DRM is aging and it&amp;rsquo;s in our interest to complete &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.freebsd.org/Graphics/Update_DRM_generic_code_to_Linux_3.8&#34;&gt;its
update&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During discussions with the many &lt;strong&gt;Nouveau developers&lt;/strong&gt; present, it
appears that porting Nouveau to FreeBSD shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be that hard. The
greatest difficulty is TTM and we have it for the Radeon driver already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding other kernel drivers, I talked with some &lt;strong&gt;ARM developers&lt;/strong&gt;
about the license issue, because most of the drivers are GPLv2
currently. Their choice of the license was most of the time a default
choice, not something they firmly want. In fact, they would love to see
the hardware supported by other OS and therefore are open to changing
that, though they are of course not alone to decide. A transition to a
dual GPLv2/MIT license model is already underway for the AllWinner GPU
driver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spoke to two &lt;strong&gt;libinput maintainers&lt;/strong&gt; about what was required to port
it to FreeBSD. &lt;a href=&#34;http://who-t.blogspot.fr/2014/09/libinput-common-input-stack-for-wayland.html&#34;&gt;libinput&amp;rsquo;s
goal&lt;/a&gt;
is to unify input handling for both X.Org and Wayland, instead of having
multiple &lt;code&gt;xf86-input-*&lt;/code&gt; drivers. It depends on evdev which is &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.freebsd.org/SummerOfCode2014/evdev_Touchscreens&#34;&gt;being
added to FreeBSD&lt;/a&gt;
(GSoC 2014). It also depends on epoll which can be replaced by kqueue.
Finally, it optionally uses udev for input devices discovery, something
we can implement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking about &lt;strong&gt;udev&lt;/strong&gt;, I learned that it&amp;rsquo;s not going away anytime
soon, according to people close to systemd developers. This contradicts
what we heard 6 month ago at FOSDEM. That&amp;rsquo;s why we may resume the
udev implementation project we planned some time ago, and add it to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/freebsd/libdevq&#34;&gt;libdevq&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bsd-track:bf650b87c593bc5b43a8309cddeddd77&#34;&gt;The BSD track&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the last day, there was a BSD track where &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.x.org/wiki/Events/XDC2014/XDC2014TigeotDragonFlyBSD/&#34;&gt;François
Tigeot&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.x.org/wiki/Events/XDC2014/XDC2014HerrbOpenBSD/&#34;&gt;Matthieu
Herrb&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.x.org/wiki/Events/XDC2014/XDC2014PedronFreeBSD/&#34;&gt;and I&lt;/a&gt;
presented the status of the graphics stack on our respective OS. I was
first and, beside a couple questions, I had mostly kind comments from
people appreciating our presence and efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, I would like to thank Martin Peres for organizing this
XDC and for encouraging us during last FOSDEM to talk about the BSDs.
I&amp;rsquo;d like to thank everyone for the really friendly moments we had. We
all arranged to meet at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://fosdem.org/2015/&#34;&gt;next FOSDEM&lt;/a&gt; in
Brussels, I&amp;rsquo;m definitely looking forward to it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slides and videos of all talks are linked in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.x.org/wiki/Events/XDC2014/Program/&#34;&gt;program on the
X.Org wiki&lt;/a&gt;.
Videos are also available from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCXlH5v1PkEhjzLFTUTm_U7g&#34;&gt;X.Org YouTube
Channel&lt;/a&gt;.
I posted &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/dumbbell/sets/72157648322164320/&#34;&gt;pictures on
Flickr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>