<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Kernel on The FreeBSD Graphics Team</title>
    <link>http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/categories/the-kernel/</link>
    <description>Recent content in The Kernel on The FreeBSD Graphics Team</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2014 20:10:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/categories/the-kernel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>vt(4) enabled by default</title>
      <link>http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/post/vt-enabled-by-default/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2014 20:10:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/post/vt-enabled-by-default/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;vt(4), the new console driver, is &lt;a href=&#34;http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/https://svnweb.freebsd.org/base?view=revision&amp;amp;revision=274085&#34;&gt;enabled out-of-the-box in FreeBSD
11-CURRENT&lt;/a&gt;
(the development branch of FreeBSD) as of today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who don&amp;rsquo;t know it yet, vt(4) brings important features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It &lt;strong&gt;supports Unicode&lt;/strong&gt; and double-width characters. It finally allows
to use an UTF-8 locale.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It &lt;strong&gt;integrates with the new kernel video drivers&lt;/strong&gt;. That means that
you can switch from an X session to the console and back. syscons(4)
was never taught about the KMS drivers, and this was a major
regression for users because the screen was blank when vt-switching or
terminating the X server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;vt(4) has still some issues. Furthermore, it lacks some features
compared to syscons(4). Known issues are &lt;a href=&#34;http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/https://wiki.freebsd.org/Newcons#Known_Issues&#34;&gt;listed in the
wiki&lt;/a&gt; and/or
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/buglist.cgi?keywords=vt&amp;amp;list_id=28354&amp;amp;resolution=---&#34;&gt;recorded in Bugzilla using the &amp;ldquo;vt” keyword&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Refer to the associated &lt;code&gt;UPDATING&lt;/code&gt; entry to get information about updated
console settings in &lt;code&gt;/etc/rc.conf&lt;/code&gt; or how to select syscons(4).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why kernel video drivers?</title>
      <link>http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/post/why-kernel-video-drivers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2014 20:20:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dumbbell.github.io/graphics-team/post/why-kernel-video-drivers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many people wonder why video drivers are moved to the kernel. The
previous way of doing things was working fine and was supported by all
Unix. Now, they are afraid of switching to those kernel drivers because
they don&amp;rsquo;t understand the reason behind them and have heard about
instability and unequal levels of support between different OS versions
and GPU makers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll try to explain the reasons I know, in the hope you&amp;rsquo;ll better
understand and accept this major change in the way we use video cards
nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;X server was an operating system by itself&lt;/strong&gt;: it was able to
scan the PCI bus to find video devices and it manages the video
memory. That&amp;rsquo;s why it could work on many incompatible kernels: it
doesn&amp;rsquo;t use any of its facilities. This approach has obviously many
major issues, detailed in the following bullets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;kernel and the X server were both managing hardware&lt;/strong&gt;. This was
far from elegant and broke features such as suspend/resume.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;X server required root privileges&lt;/strong&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s why it&amp;rsquo;s
installed with the &amp;ldquo;setuid” bit set, otherwise a regular
couldn&amp;rsquo;t start an X session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;performance was terrible&lt;/strong&gt; compared to platforms (eg. Microsoft
Windows) where the video drivers are in the kernel (like any other
drivers).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The architecture of X and the tighly integrated drivers made it &lt;strong&gt;hard
to reuse the code&lt;/strong&gt; if one wants to implement an alternative, such as
Wayland. But that was true for the system console too: it needed to
drive the video card.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GPGPU wasn&amp;rsquo;t possible&lt;/strong&gt; without running an X session, because only
the X server was capable of handling the GPU.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It &lt;strong&gt;wasn&amp;rsquo;t possible to access the GPU from a virtual machine&lt;/strong&gt;, for
the same reason as above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the kernel drivers address or will address all of these issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding GPGPU using free open-source software on FreeBSD, it&amp;rsquo;s still
a work in progress. A &amp;ldquo;Hello World” OpenCL program works on my
machine, but more packaging and polishing is needed to have something
working out-of-the-box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The X server still requires root privileges today on FreeBSD because
we lack the APIs and tools to allow the server to gain access to input
devices in a secure manner (remember, the system console needs the
keyboard too).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About using the GPU from a VM, we are still far from this goal, even on
Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>